Rosenthal, Donald; Papers apap202
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Donald B. Rosenthal Papers
1982-2004
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Rosenthal, Donald B.,1937-
apap202
1.8 cubic ft.
Documents twenty years of Dr. Rosenthal's research into the history of gay and lesbian activism and the AIDS crisis.
Biographical History
Born in 1937, Donald B. Rosenthal was Professor Emeritus of Political Science at the University of Buffalo, State University of New York, where he studied and taught from 1964 to 1999. He served as Department Chairman for five of his 27 years as a full professor. His research interests included lesbian and gay community activism and the responses of New York State cities to the HIV/AIDS epidemic. In 2000, he retired to Charlotte, North Carolina.
Dr. Rosenthal died on December 5, 2014 aged 77 at his residence in Charlotte. He was survived by his partner of 28 years, David G. Scott.
Scope and Contents
The Donald B. Rosenthal Papers include an extensive collection of interviews with Capital District activists, an assortment of print publications regarding AIDS, and a series of material documenting the activities of the Capital District Gay and Lesbian Community Council (CDGLCC). The results of Rosenthal's research are represented by a collection of his own papers and lectures on gay activists' role in municipal politics and their responses to the spread of AIDS.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into 4 file series.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were transferred to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives in 2005-2006 by Donald Rosenthal.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Gay activists -- New York (State).; Lesbian activists -- New York (State).; AIDS (Disease) -- United States -- Prevention -- Citizen participation.; Political scientists -- United States.; Interviews.; Newsletters.; Periodicals.; Programs.; Manuscripts (document genre); Clippings (information artifacts); Articles.; Human Sexuality and Gender Identity; Medicine and Health Care; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Rosenthal, Donald B., 1937-,; St. John, Keith.; Post, Libby.; Capital District Gay and Lesbian Community Council (Albany, N.Y.); New York (State). AIDS Institute
- Research Material, 1986-1999; 1
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains material collected by Professor Rosenthal during the course of his research. It contains an extensive collection of transcriptions of Rosenthal's interviews with various Capital District gay and lesbian activists. Interview subjects include Albany Common Council member Keith St. John (the first openly gay African-American to be elected to public office in the United States), Father Ron Gerber of the Albany Damien Center, activist Libby Post, and numerous other individuals involved in the movement for gay and lesbian rights. They discuss matters such as the history of the GLBT community in the Capital District, its role in Albany municipal politics and New York State politics, and the impact of AIDS on the community. These transcriptions are arranged chronologically; an alphabetical index which cross-references names with dates is available in Box 1, Folder 1. The series also includes a file of publications on the AIDS crisis, including reports by the New York State Department of Health AIDS Institute (NYSDOHAI), other New York State agencies, and a number of federal agencies and private nonprofits.
  - Interview Transcripts (includes index to all transcripts), 1988-1989 (Box 1 (1-Research Material), Folder 1)
  - Interview Transcripts, 1990 (Box 1 (1-Research Material), Folder 2)
  - Interview Transcripts, 1992 (Box 1 (1-Research Material), Folder 3)
  - Interview Transcripts, 1994-1999 (Box 1 (1-Research Material), Folder 4)
  - Publications - New York State Task Force on Bias-Related Violence, 1988 (Box 1 (1-Research Material), Folder 5)
  - Publications - Needle Exchange Programs, 1995-1996 (Box 1 (1-Research Material), Folder 6)
  - Publications - New York State Reports on AIDS, general, 1986-1991 (Box 2 (1-Research Material), Folder 1)
  - Publications - New York State Department of Social Services - AIDS Update(Newsletter), 1987-1992 (Box 2 (1-Research Material), Folder 2)
  - Publications - New York State Department of Health AIDS Institute (NYSDOHAI) - Focus on AIDS in New York State(Newsletter), 1991-1992 (Box 2 (1-Research Material), Folder 3)
  - Publications - New York State Department of Health AIDS Institute (NYSDOHAI) - Reports, 1991-1994 (Box 2 (1-Research Material), Folder 4)
  - Publications - New York State Department of Health AIDS Institute (NYSDOHAI) - Reports, 1994-1996 (Box 2 (1-Research Material), Folder 5)
  - Publications - White House National AIDS Strategy, 1997 (Box 3 (1-Research Material), Folder 1)
  - Publications - Federal, Private and Nonprofit Publications on AIDS Crisis, 1987-1992 (Box 3 (1-Research Material), Folder 2)
  - Publications - Federal, Private and Nonprofit Publications on AIDS Crisis, 1990-1997 (Box 3 (1-Research Material), Folder 3)
- Manuscripts & Publications, 1992-1996; 2
  This series contains drafts and published copies of Dr. Rosenthal's academic work on the subjects of gay community activism and the AIDS crisis, including articles in Urban Affairs Review and Polity and an address to the American Political Science Association. Items are organized alphabetically by title.
  - "Albany Notes" (typescript), 1994 (Box 3 (2-Manuscripts & Publications), Folder 4)
  - Dilemmas in the Development of AIDS Service Organizations in Upstate New York." Address to American Political Science Association (typescript), 1990 (Box 3 (2-Manuscripts & Publications), Folder 4)
  - "Gay and Lesbian Political Mobilization and Regime Responsiveness in Four New York Cities." Urban Affairs Review Vol. 32, No. 1 (article photocopy and 3 drafts), 1996 September (Box 3 (2-Manuscripts & Publications), Folder 4)
  - "Who 'Owns' AIDS Service Organizations? Governance Accountability in Non-Profit Organizations." Polity Vol. 29, No. 1 (offprint and 2 drafts), 1996 Fall (Box 3 (2-Manuscripts & Publications), Folder 4)
- Subject File, 1985-2001; 3
  This series contains several subject files related to various gay rights and AIDS prevention initiatives. Items within each file include leaflets, correspondence and news clippings.
  - AIDS Council of Northeastern New York, 1989-1995 (Box 3 (3-Subject File), Folder 5)
  - Albany Human Rights Ordinance, 1992-1995 (Box 3 (3-Subject File), Folder 6)
  - Empire State Pride Agenda, 1990-2001 (Box 3 (3-Subject File), Folder 7)
  - Housing Works, 1993-1998 (Box 3 (3-Subject File), Folder 8)
  - Organizations, Miscellaneous, 1988-1999 (Box 3 (3-Subject File), Folder 9)
  - Rochester, NY, 1985-1997 (Box 3 (3-Subject File), Folder 10)
  - Support Ministries, Inc./ Ahana House, 1992 (Box 3 (3-Subject File), Folder 11)
- Capital District Gay and Lesbian Community Council (CDGLCC), 1982-2004; 4
  This series consists of material related to the Capital District Gay and Lesbian Community Council (CDGLCC). It consists primarily of an extensive run of the Council's monthly periodical, Community, which is partial from 1982-1991 and 2001-2003 and complete from 1992-2000. (Note that several issues from the years 1999-2000 are housed in an oversized box at the end of the series.) The series also includes fliers and programs for events held by the Council, news clippings related to the Council and its members, a small assortment of administrative files, and issues of the Council's quarterly member newsletter, MemberNews.
  - Community, 1982-1991 (Box 4 (4-Capital District Gay and Lesbian Community Council), Folder 1)
  - Community, 1992 (Box 4 (4-Capital District Gay and Lesbian Community Council), Folder 2)
  - Community, 1993 (Box 4 (4-Capital District Gay and Lesbian Community Council), Folder 3)
  - Community, 1994 (Box 4 (4-Capital District Gay and Lesbian Community Council), Folder 4)
  - Community, 1995 (Box 4 (4-Capital District Gay and Lesbian Community Council), Folder 5)
  - Community, 1996 (Box 5 (4-Capital District Gay and Lesbian Community Council), Folder 1)
  - Community, 1997 (Box 5 (4-Capital District Gay and Lesbian Community Council), Folder 2)
  - Community, 1998 (Box 5 (4-Capital District Gay and Lesbian Community Council), Folder 3)
  - Community, 1999 (Box 5 (4-Capital District Gay and Lesbian Community Council), Folder 4)
  - Community, 2000-2003 (Box 6 (4-Capital District Gay and Lesbian Community Council), Folder 1)
  - Administrative Files, 1988-1998 (Box 6 (4-Capital District Gay and Lesbian Community Council), Folder 2)
  - Event Publications, 1989-2004 (Box 6 (4-Capital District Gay and Lesbian Community Council), Folder 3)
  - News Clippings, 1988-1997 (Box 6 (4-Capital District Gay and Lesbian Community Council), Folder 4)
  - Research notes; MemberNews, 1994-1997 (Box 6 (4-Capital District Gay and Lesbian Community Council), Folder 5)
  - Community, 1999-2000 (Oversized 7, Folder 1)